# Xing Liu

https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4637-0109

xing.liu@njit.edu

https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Zbw gAwAAAAJ

+1 (973) 642-7239

https://hint1412.github.io/

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My Mission is to leverage AI for designing *mechanically resilient* engineering materials and structures (with exceptional strength and fracture/fatigue resistance) for aerospace and energy applications and enabling *more socioresilient* utilization of these materials throughout their *entire* life cycle. The success of the mission hinges on the integration of *multiscale modeling* (e.g., atomistic modeling, crystal plasticity modeling, phase field modeling), *advanced machine learning* (e.g., generative AI), and *multiscale materials characterization*.

**Scientific Endeavors** that underpin my mission include i) decoding the *mechanics of strength* for materials exhibiting exceptional structural, microstructural, and/or compositional *heterogeneity*, *e.g.*, complex concentrated alloys, additively manufactured materials, ceramic composites, ii) developing *experimentally* validated models with *uncertainty quantification* to predict the *inelastic* deformation and *fracture* of materials under *normal* and *extreme* conditions, iii) devising *multiphysics* methodologies for *manipulating* material microstructures and for *rejuvenating* and *repairing* damaged heterogeneous materials. My lab will be open to both computational and experimental collaborations, and we will continue to broaden our research interests.

Concurrently with the research thrust described above, I am committed to constructing a machine learning-enabled open-access platform for materials characterization.

#### EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

## New Jersey Institute of Technology, USA

Assistant Professor, Department of Mechanical and Industrial Engineering

September 2024 – Present

## Georgia Institute of Technology, USA

Postdoctoral Fellow, George W. Woodruff School of Mechanical Engineering

August 2022 – August 2024

Working with Prof. Ting Zhu

## **Brown University, USA**

Postdoctoral Research Associate, School of Engineering

February 2022 – July 2022

Working with Profs. Brian W. Sheldon, Nitin P. Padture, Huajian Gao

## **EDUCATION**

## Ph.D. Brown University, USA

2014 - 2021

Research Assistant, Solid Mechanics, School of Engineering

Dissertation: Integrated simulation, machine learning and experimental approaches in small-scale mechanical characterization of materials

Dissertation Committee: Prof. Huajian Gao (advisor), Prof. Brian W. Sheldon, Prof. Nitin P. Padture

# **B.E.** Tsinghua University, CHINA

2010 - 2014

Tsien Hsue-Shen Elite Class in Mechanics, Department of Engineering Mechanics

#### AWARDS & HONORS

Outstanding Reviewer Award, Acta/Scripta Materialia

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

<ul><li>Instructor, Stress Analysis, NJIT</li></ul>	Fall 2024
<ul> <li>Guest Lecturer, Linear Elasticity, Georgia Tech</li> </ul>	Spring 2024
<ul> <li>Guest Lecturer, Mechanics of Deformable Bodies, Georgia Tech</li> </ul>	Fall 2023
<ul> <li>Guest Lecturer, Statics, Georgia Tech</li> </ul>	Spring 2023
<ul> <li>Teaching Assistant, Advanced Engineering Mechanics, Brown</li> </ul>	Spring 2017

# PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS († AUTHORS WITH EQUAL CONTRIBUTIONS)

- [1] C.E. Athanasiou, X. Liu, H. Gao, "A Perspective on Democratizing Mechanical Testing: Harnessing Artificial Intelligence to Advance Sustainable Material Adoption and Decentralized Manufacturing", *Journal of Applied Mechanics* (2024).
- [2] X. Liu, C.E. Athanasiou, C. López-Pernía, T. Zhu, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Tailoring the toughening effects in two-dimensional nanomaterial-reinforced ceramic matrix composites", *Journal of Applied Mechanics* (2024).
- [3] S. Stangebye, X. Liu, L. Daza-Llanos, Y. Yang, T. Zhu, J. Kacher, O. Pierron, "Comparison of electrical sensing and image analysis for in situ transmission electron microscopy nanomechanical testing of thin films", *Thin Solid Films* (2023).
- [4] Z. Dai, M.C. Doyle, X. Liu, M. Hu, Q. Wang, C.E. Athanasiou, Y. Liu, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, S.F. Liu, N.P. Padture, "The mechanical behavior of metal-halide perovskites: Elasticity, plasticity, fracture, and creep", *Scripta Materialia* (2023).
- [5] C.E. Athanasiou<sup>†</sup>, <u>X. Liu</u><sup>†</sup>, B. Zhang<sup>†</sup>, T. Cai, C. Ramirez, N.P. Padture, J. Lou, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Integrated simulation, machine learning, and experimental approach to characterizing fracture instability in indentation pillar-splitting of materials", *Journal of the Mechanics and Physics of Solids* (2022).
- [6] C.E. Athanasiou<sup>†</sup>, <u>X. Liu</u><sup>†</sup>, M.Y. Jin, E. Nimon, S. Visco, C. Lee, M. Park, J. Yun, N.P. Padture, H. Gao, B.W. Sheldon, "Rate-dependent deformation of amorphous sulfide glass electrolytes for solid-state batteries", *Cell Reports Physical Science* (2022).
- [7] Z. Dai, S. Li, X. Liu, M. Chen, C.E. Athanasiou, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, P. Guo, N.P. Padture, "Dual-interface reinforced flexible perovskite solar cells for enhanced performance and mechanical reliability", *Advanced Materials* (2022).
- [8] X. Liu<sup>†</sup>, C.E. Athanasiou<sup>†</sup>, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Knowledge extraction and transfer in data-driven fracture mechanics", *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences* (2021).
- [9] B. Zhang<sup>†</sup>, X. Liu<sup>†</sup>, H. Guo<sup>†</sup>, K. Yang, G. Gao, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, J. Lou, "Quantitative in-situ study of strength-governed interfacial failure between h-BN and polymer-derived ceramic", *Acta Materialia* (2021).
- [10] X. Liu, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "A machine learning approach to fracture mechanics problems", *Acta Materialia* (2020).
- [11] A.K. Dickerson, X. Liu, T. Zhu, D.L. Hu, "Fog spontaneously folds mosquito wings", *Physics of Fluids* (2015).

## INVITED/CONTRIBUTED CONFERENCE TALKS

[1] X. Liu, "<u>Keynote</u> Talk – Integrated Simulation, Machine learning, and Experimental Approaches in Small-Scale Mechanical Characterization of Materials", *The Society of Engineering Science (SES) Annual Technical Meeting*, October 2022.

- [2] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, T. Zhu, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Tailoring toughening effects in two-dimensional nanomaterial-reinforced ceramic matrix composites", *The Society of Engineering Science (SES) Annual Technical Meeting*, October 2023.
- [3] **X. Liu**, T. Zhu, "Contributed Talk Investigating precipitate hardening through discrete dislocation analysis", *The Society of Engineering Science (SES) Annual Technical Meeting*, October 2023.
- [4] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, "Contributed Talk Integrating Simulation, Machine Learning, and Experimental Approaches for High-Throughput Small-Scale Fracture Investigations", *15<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Fracture (ICF15)*, June 2023.
- [5] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Knowledge extraction and transfer in data-driven fracture mechanics", *ASCE Engineering Mechanics Institute (EMI) Conference*, June 2023.
- [6] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Integrating Simulation, Machine Learning, and Experimental Approaches in Small-Scale Mechanical Characterization of Materials", *The Minerals, Metals & Materials Society (TMS) 2023 Annual Meeting & Exhibition*, March 2023.
- [7] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, B. Zhang, N.P. Padture, J. Lou, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk Integrated cohesive zone and J-integral approaches to characterizing indentation-induced pillar fracture instability", 19<sup>th</sup> U.S. National Congress on Theoretical and Applied Mechanics (USNC/TAM), June 2022.
- [8] **X. Liu**, C.E. Athanasiou, N.P. Padture, B.W. Sheldon, H. Gao, "Contributed Talk A machine learning approach to fracture mechanics problems", 2020 Virtual Materials Research Society (MRS) Fall Meeting & Exhibit, November 2020.